<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before Their Majesties K. James II and Q. Mary at their coronation in Westminster-Abby, April 23, 1685 by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12271255</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12271255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63889)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before Their Majesties K. James II and Q. Mary at their coronation in Westminster-Abby, April 23, 1685 by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by Andrew Crook and Samuel Helsham, and are to be sold by Samuel Helsham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1685?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Coronation.</term>
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694 --  Coronation.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 1st, XXIX, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before THEIR MAJESTIES K. JAMES II. and Q. MARY. AT Their CORONATION IN VVeſtminſter-Abby, April 23. 1685.</p>
            <p>By Francis Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Biſhop of ELY, and Lord Alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>DUBLIN, Re-printed by <hi>Andrew Crook</hi> and <hi>Samuel Helſham;</hi> And are to be Sold by <hi>Samuel Helſham</hi> at the <hi>Colledge-Arms</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58262:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58262:2"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached before their Majeſties King James II. and Queen Mary, at their Coronation, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 CHRON. XXIX. 23.</bibl>
Then Solomon ſat on the Throne of the Lord as King, inſtead of David his Father, and proſpered, and all Iſrael obeyed him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>THen Solomon ſate on the throne of the Lord. Then,</hi> that is to ſay, on the day of his <hi>Coronation,</hi> which is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in the foregoing Verſe<hi>: Then,</hi> when <hi>they anointed him.</hi> This may ſuffice to ſhew, my Text is ſuitable enough to the preſent royal Solemnity. But if I had any mind to parallel all the greatneſs and ſolemn glories of this day from the ſtory of that King, I ſhould be forc'd, as great as King <hi>Solomon</hi> was, to borrow ſome Illuſtrious Remarks from ſeveral other of his beſt days, beſides that of his Coronation. For when <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> was <hi>Enthroniz'd,</hi> no Temple was then built, or ſo much as begun: but to day we have ſeen a ſpectacle full of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſplendor in <hi>God's Houſe,</hi> and filling our hearts with joy. We have ſeen a King ſtanding, as <hi>Solomon</hi> (on the day when he dedicated the Temple) <hi>ſtood before the Altar of the Lord in the preſence of all the congregation of Iſrael, and ſpread forth his hands.</hi> Nay, we have ſeen his Majeſty in an humbler, that is, a devouter poſture. To day we have ſeen another ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of magnificent Piety, a Queen, for whom it were too low a compariſon, ſhould I compare her to her that was rais'd immediately to a Throne near to that of K. <hi>Solomon, then, when</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>his mother crown'd him</hi> again <hi>in the day of his eſpouſals;</hi> But a Queen, the moſt faithful companion of her royal Husband's ſufferings and hard travels; the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be now the Conſort of all his Triumphs. We have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58262:3"/>
ſeen her alſo like her ſelf; that is, like <hi>Humility</hi> it ſelf, which is <hi>the Queen of Vertues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Story of <hi>K. Solomon,</hi> could I bring skill to ſet it forth, would furniſh an entertainment for the devotions both of a Royal Audience, and a mixt Aſſembly. For the <hi>King</hi> in my Text made himſelf his Text; He made his own life the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of an excellent Sermon. He was pleaſed to ſtile him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Preacher, as well as the King in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> He once had been inſtructed by the King, his Father, <hi>the man after God's own heart;</hi> but afterward he was <hi>taught of God,</hi> on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be ſet up for an everlaſting Guide, by the rules and directions he ſhould leave to all other Princes and people.</p>
            <p>To begin then where they began with him in the Text: 'Tis ſaid, <hi>they made Solomon, the ſon of David, King the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> time was then when <hi>Adonijah exalted himſelf, and ſaid, I will be King;</hi> when <hi>he prepar'd himſelf Chariots, and Horſemen, and fifty men to run before him.</hi> But <hi>the race is not always to the ſwifteſt,</hi> nor to him that ſets out ſooneſt for <hi>Popularity;</hi> yet then it was high time for <hi>David</hi> to declare the <hi>Succeſſion;</hi> for then he was told, <hi>The eyes of all Iſrael are upon thee, that thou ſhouldeſt tell them</hi> (on ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I ſhall ſhew anon, that God had told him already) <hi>who ſhould ſit upon the Throne of my Lord the King after him.</hi> Thereupon <hi>Solomon</hi> was declared, and preſently anointed to ſucceed. But becauſe the Ceremony then was perform'd in a kind of tumultuary haſt, 'tis now repeated at more leiſure with greater ſtate.</p>
            <p>To keep my ſelf within ſome compaſs, and from wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in ſuch a world of matter as the Story of K. <hi>Solomon</hi> would offer me, I ſhall be willingly confin'd to theſe <hi>four Points,</hi> through which we may ſee K. <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt. That his Title was firm and good:</hi> 'Tis ſaid here, <hi>He ſate on the Throne of the Lord,</hi> and he ſate there, <hi>as King,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>David</hi> his Father. And,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> For <hi>his Government;</hi> that <hi>was as</hi> good as his Title: His management was ſuch as became ſo wiſe a King as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> And,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58262:3"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly, His people were an obedient people;</hi> and all Iſrael o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd him.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly, The Bleſſing of God was upon him and his Government. 'Tis ſaid,</hi> He proſper'd.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Firſt</hi> place for his <hi>Title,</hi> to make that good, if this be not Argument enough, that 'tis ſaid here, <hi>He ſate on the throne of the Lord;</hi> and that he ſate there <hi>as King, inſtead of David his Father;</hi> let me farther obſerve to you, That he was a King of God's own <hi>Nomination,</hi> to prevent diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of <hi>David,</hi> 1. Chron. 22. 9. <hi>Behold, a Son ſhall be born to thee his name ſhall be Solomon, and I will eſtabliſh the throne of his kingdom.</hi> His Brother <hi>Adonijah,</hi> after his vain Attempt to ſeize the Crown, makes this expreſs acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>Solomon's Right</hi> to the Kingdom, <hi>Tho' it were mine from the People, yet it was his from the Lord:</hi> For God's Choice and the People's are not always the ſame.</p>
            <p>But if this were the Caſe, that he was rais'd to the Throne, not properly by the <hi>King</hi> his <hi>Father,</hi> much leſs by the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> but by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, how comes it to be ſaid here, <hi>They made him King? They,</hi> that is, <hi>all the Congregation.</hi> Were they the King-makers then? Were they the Original of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Power? Had they it firſt in themſelves? Elſe how could they impart it? Towards the clearing of this, be pleaſed to compare the ſtory of another King's Coronation in the <hi>Book of Kings,</hi> with that ſelf ſame ſtory in the <hi>Book of Chronicles:</hi> And whereas in one place we read, <hi>the People anointed Joaſh</hi> we find in the other Place, that <hi>Jehojadah, the High Prieſt, and his Sons, anointed him;</hi> ſo not the <hi>people's</hi> Anointed, but <hi>the Lord's Anointed.</hi> Only the People ſtood by, as they do here and expreſs their unanimous good Will with ſuch loud Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations as you heard e'ne now: not that we imagine our united voices contribute any thing of <hi>Right</hi> to our <hi>Hereditary</hi> Prince; but to ſhew that if the Kingdom were <hi>Elective,</hi> we think him moſt worthy to be King. But 'tis moſt plain, and moſt evident, that God by his ſpecial appointment ſet over his People, the firſt three ſucceeding Kings, <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon;</hi> and where ever 'tis ſaid the People <hi>made</hi> them (or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58262:4"/>
any other) <hi>Kings;</hi> no more is meant, but that the People own'd them as Kings of God's making But that immediate Deſignation of their Kings from Heaven was to ceaſe one day, and the Kingdom was to be <hi>Hereditary.</hi> This appears from the Concluſion of thoſe <hi>Proviſional ſtatutes</hi> Deut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 17. thoſe precepts for the King that ſhould <hi>be ſet over them that he may prolong his days in the Kingdom, he and his Children in the middeſt of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>Right</hi> to Empire was <hi>thus</hi> viſible, ſo</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> His other Royal Qualifications were moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous; whether his natural Endowments be conſider'd, or his ſupernatural Gifts to fit him yet more for Government. When God bid him <hi>ask what he would,</hi> he ask of God nothing but <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and he had that he askt, with an overplus, not only of all other excellent things: but alſo of more <hi>Wiſdom</hi> than he knew how to ask of God, before he receiv'd it. He is reckon'd about eighteen years of Age, when he began to Reign, ſo that he ſtiles himſelf <hi>a Child;</hi> tho, his dying Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave him that great Character, as no more than his due, <hi>Thou art a wiſe Man, and do therefore according to thy Wiſdom.</hi> How wiſely did he foreſee any coming danger? How perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well skill'd was he in the times and ſeaſons? <hi>When</hi> and <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom,</hi> or <hi>what ſort</hi> of men, it was fit to ſhew <hi>Juſtice</hi> or <hi>Mercy?</hi> preſently he made it appear how true it is, that being in a place of Government, ſhews what a man is. For inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he penetrated the ambitious Intrigueing deſign of <hi>Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> that was playing an after-game for the Kingdom, labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet up himſelf again upon a new Alliance, that had a powerful intereſt in the Court. But, tho, <hi>Solomon</hi> had Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd his Rebellion (yet ſo as to keep him ſtill on his good Behaviour) and had promis'd him a favourable Pretection, <hi>if he would ſhew himſelf a worthy man;</hi> yet his Juſtice would ſpare him no longer, when once he made himſelf unworthy of that Mercy. Then his early ſeverity upon <hi>Joab,</hi> whom K. <hi>David</hi> going out of the world, had delivered over not as a <hi>Traytor,</hi> but as a <hi>Murderer,</hi> to the righteous Judgment of K. <hi>Solomon:</hi> That was a moſt effectual Declaration to all his Subjects, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58262:4"/>
they muſt expect no more pardons in the caſe of Murder, ſince neither the greatneſs of his paſt ſervices, nor his nearneſs of Blood to the Royal Family, could ſecure <hi>Joab</hi> from falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that Law, <hi>He that ſheddeth man's Blood, by man ſhall his Blood be ſhed.</hi> But at the ſame time, behold the Clemency of K. <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>Abiather,</hi> becauſe he had been a faithful old Servant to K. <hi>David,</hi> and a <hi>Sufferer</hi> with him; tho, he had been a great Offender with <hi>Adonijah;</hi> nevertheleſs K. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> remitted him both his Life and Eſtate. He gave a noble Inſtance, how proper objects of Royal Goodneſs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, are <hi>old Royaliſts,</hi> tho, ſome of them may have been miſlead to make falſe Steps, and have fallen into fatal Errors<hi>:</hi> On the other ſide for <hi>Shimei,</hi> that had <hi>curſt K. David,</hi> and <hi>flung ſtones at his Head</hi> in the day of his diſtreſs; they do wrong to the dying King, who think he retracted his Act of pardoning <hi>Shimei</hi>'s Life, when he bid his Son, <hi>Hold him not guiltleſs,</hi> that is, Treat him not like an Innocent perſon: And when he ſpoke what follows there, not as a King command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but foret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling (as even his natural Divination might ſerve him to do) <hi>his hoar head thou ſhalt,</hi> or thou wilt <hi>bring down to the Grave with Blood</hi> (for ſo it may well be tranſlated) on Suppoſition that ſuch a one as <hi>Shimei</hi> would offend again: Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> did like himſelf, to ſet ſuch a reſtleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Spirit his bounds, which he ſhould not Paſs, and when he tranſgreſt afreſh, then to call his old Sins to remembrance, and to take that Life, which ſuch an execrable Wretch had forfeited the ſecond time,</p>
            <p n="3">III But as <hi>Solomon</hi> was a famous good Governor, ſo <hi>third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> his People were eminently Loyal. <hi>All Iſrael obey'd him.</hi> Of which there follows upon my Text a farther Explication; <hi>all the princes,</hi> that is, the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> or the <hi>Senate</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd his juſt Soveraignty over them. <hi>And the mighty men,</hi> that is, the <hi>Military</hi> men made their Addreſſes to him, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the power of the <hi>Militia</hi> was ſolely his. And <hi>all the ſons likewiſe of K.</hi> David <hi>ſubmitted themſelves to</hi> Solomon <hi>the King;</hi> for <hi>Adonijah</hi> had called them all, except <hi>Solomon,</hi> to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his taking upon him to be King; but now that <hi>cabal</hi> was diſſolv'd,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58262:5"/>
&amp; their <hi>leader</hi> was taken off; their faction grew weary of it ſelf and the King no doubt receiv'd their Submiſſion with a Goodneſs well becoming his own Greatneſs. But tho, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll his <hi>Subjects</hi> yielded him ſuch entire <hi>Obedience,</hi> yet ſtill they ſerv'd him as <hi>Freemen,</hi> not as <hi>Slaves.</hi> It was <hi>his</hi> greateſt <hi>Honour,</hi> as well as the happyneſs of his <hi>People,</hi> that as Gods Service is perfect Freedom, ſo in Imitation of it, was that of <hi>God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent;</hi> for we are told in the <hi>Book of Kings;</hi> that <hi>of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael did Solomon make no Bondmen.</hi> but as it follows there <hi>They were men of War, and his Servants, and his Princes and his Captains, and Rulers of his Chariots, and his Horſemen.</hi> And thus <hi>all Iſrael obey'd him,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV<hi>:</hi> But all this had never been ſo happily Adminiſtred, had there not been a <hi>fourth</hi> Concurrent of more Conſequence than all the <hi>three</hi> foregoing; Had there not been an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Bleſſing of God,</hi> not only upon that Great <hi>Prince,</hi> but upon all his good <hi>Subjects;</hi> had not he been <hi>Religious,</hi> as well as <hi>Politick;</hi> and had not they been a People capable of that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. But <hi>He</hi> and <hi>They</hi> were duly qualified for it: They joyn'd with him, to derive it upon His Sacred Head, and from thence upon their own, like the <hi>Oyntment upon Aaron's head, which ran down and diffus'd its ſelf</hi> over the whole Body. He Built the <hi>Temple;</hi> they all Contributed. He brought up the <hi>Ark</hi> of God; they attended it. Sacrific'd whole <hi>Hecatombs;</hi> they at the ſame time kept a <hi>ſolemn Feaſt</hi> to the Lord. He made that fervent <hi>prayer</hi> to God; they all ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to it. He bleſt, the People, He bleſt God: God ratifi'd the <hi>Kings Bleſſing</hi> upon the <hi>People,</hi> God return'd the <hi>Divine Bleſſing</hi> upon the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mid'ſt of all this 'tis ſaid, <hi>He proſpered.</hi> How could it be otherwiſe than ſo? Great peace and plenty at home, with as much honour and intereſt abroad. The Native Wealth of his own Country was improv'd, and Commerce increaſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily; all <hi>foreign</hi> good things were <hi>imported<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and made his, by the particular care he took of what concern'd <hi>Navigation.</hi> His City the Seat of Empire was then more than ever <hi>the joy of the whole Earth.</hi> What could be added to all this Proſperity except Victory over his Enemies? Yes, it was a vaſt addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58262:5"/>
to his almoſt unparallel'd felicity, that he had no enemies He was able to ſend this Meſſage to his friend K. <hi>Hiram, now the Lord my God hath given me reſt on every ſide, ſo that there is neither Adverſary nor evil Occurrent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it was with him till he left off Serving God. Then indeed God was angry with him. Yet from the fall and riſing again of K<hi>: Solomon</hi> may be fetch't the laſt (perhaps the higheſt) Inſtance of his Bleſſedneſs: for as he ſtands a formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Example of Human Frailty: ſo we may allow him to be not only a comfortable, but alſo a moſt <hi>admirable</hi> Inſtance of the Divine Omnipotent Mercy<hi>:</hi> As he loſt <hi>himſelf</hi> after ſo many wiſe contemplations by trying thoſe coſtly experiments in ſinful pleaſures, As he forgot God &amp; himſelf, and his own godly dictates in the <hi>Book of Proverbs;</hi> ſo 'tis generally agreed that he wrote his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> as his Penetential; that he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred</hi> himſelf, &amp; <hi>turn'd to the Lord his God, that he is num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the Children of God, and his lot is among the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, to dwell no longer on the particular Story of that great King, I may ſet it down in general as certainly true, that wherever in any Prince and People all the ſame cauſes of proſperity meet together; there (and no where elſe) The like wonderful bleſſed effect will aſſuredly reſult and follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And <hi>firſt</hi> for a King and People to be happy, the King muſt have a right to his Kingdom. For how can an Uſurper expect to Reign proſperouſly? when many under his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt needs think themſelves his equals, if not his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and none can reaſonably think themſelves oblig'd to be his Subjects? And how miſerable is a King and Kingdom, when every private man, that is but audacious enough, has a fair pretence, if he can but gather force, to overturn any Settlemen that can be in ſuch a caſe: Such a <hi>Pyrat-Prince</hi> muſt be always expos'd to tempeſts; and if, like the great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> he can take any paſtime in them, he may thank his ſick fancy for the pleaſing dream. I will mention only two that were both of them royally deſcended, yet <hi>unjuſtly</hi> poſſeſs'd of this Crown: King <hi>Stephen</hi> was none of our worſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58262:6"/>
Princes, and one of the moſt valiant; but an <hi>Intruder he was,</hi> and he ſped accordingly: his Reign was the moſt turbulent of any, except that of <hi>K: John</hi> another Uſurper, and this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was reduc'd to that extremity, that he very meanly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd his Imperial Crown to the Pope, who had <hi>Interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> all publick <hi>Divine Offices</hi> in this miſerable <hi>kingdom</hi> for above ſix years; and who never afterwards mention'd that Prince but with the Title of <hi>John our Vaſſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then again, to provide well for the peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Prince and People, 'tis neceſſary not only that the <hi>Title</hi> to the Crown look fair, but that it be ſuch as is not eaſily li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be conteſted: elſe there will be <hi>Competitors,</hi> and that of it ſelf is a heavy Judgment. Nay, I add farther, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier thoſe <hi>Competitors,</hi> the more <hi>capable</hi> they are of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding all before them. As in the fatal Diſpute between <hi>Tork</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> there were two Princes, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, and <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, each of them extraordinary in their different characters: one of them accounted a <hi>Saint,</hi> the other a moſt <hi>active</hi> generous Prince: Both of them had faſt hold of <hi>the peoples affections</hi> in their ſeveral Parties, and they rent the Kingdom in pieces between them<hi>:</hi> They made our poor <hi>Countrey</hi> an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of <hi>Blood;</hi> kill'd up whole Families, and the greateſt number of both thoſe <hi>Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> till the <hi>woful controverſy was happily ended</hi> by that auſpicious Marriage, from which a Race of <hi>Kings</hi> with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right,</hi> and our preſent Gracious Sovereign is <hi>Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But as the <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> muſt be clear and right; ſo ſecondly the management of the Scepter ſhould be as wiſe as the <hi>Tenure</hi> is juſt and <hi>Royal.</hi> Our two unfortunate Kings, the <hi>Second Edward</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> had an indiſputable <hi>Right,</hi> which they could never loſe<hi>:</hi> The more was the wrong done them, though they loſt themſelves by their Male-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Government. But on the other ſide, what vaſt hopes may be juſtly conceiv'd? what bleſſed wonders may be wrought for the publick good, where the <hi>Sovereign</hi> Prince has all the dexterity, together with all the <hi>Activity</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58262:6"/>
that is neceſſary to make his motions as regular as they are vigorous, in ſo bright and ſo high a Sphere? Then will the ſaying of <hi>Solomon</hi> prove it ſelf, That <hi>the</hi> King <hi>by Judgment eſtabliſheth the Land.</hi> Nay, then it will extend to other <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms;</hi> for Kings have long hands, eſpecially ſuch a King as may hold the Balance, and give Peace and War where he pleaſes, and conſequently may give Law to other Nations; He may reach out, as <hi>Solomon</hi> did, the fruits of his wiſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to all the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But in the <hi>third place</hi> I muſt needs add, be the Title of a King as good as a Warrant from Heaven can make it; Be it ſo undoubted as Hell it ſelf can find no pretence to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it; be the King like an Angel of God for his <hi>knowledge</hi> and Conduct in the Government; yet if his Subjects <hi>will be Sons of Belial, Sons of the Devil</hi> (ſo <hi>Rebels</hi> are call'd in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) <hi>Belial,</hi> that is, <hi>abſque Jugo,</hi> men that will bear no yoke; 'tis ſtill in their power to be as miſerable as they pleaſe; Since the <hi>Wills</hi> of men are free; 'tis confeſt their leaves muſt be askt, whether they will be happy or no<hi>:</hi> Whether they will obey, and enjoy the bleſſing of Peace; or, Whether they will reſiſt, and pull down ruine upon themſelves and their poſterity. For want of a people obedient, and willing to be rul'd by a gentle hand, the beſt of Kings was moſt <hi>vilely caſt away, as if he had not been Anointed with Oyl,</hi> How dear theſe Kingdoms have paid for the <hi>Murder</hi> of that Bleſſed King, is too grievous a Reflection at this time. But one conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I would offer, though the maintenance of <hi>Religion</hi> is commonly made the moſt plauſible pretence for <hi>Rebellion</hi> (as it was for the laſt among us, and has been made uſe of ſince towards the encouraging of another,) yet <hi>Rebellion</hi> almoſt conſtantly proves (as that <hi>laſt prov'd)</hi> the means to deſtroy <hi>Religion.</hi> My meaning is not only this, that as ſoon as ever men begin to be <hi>Rebels,</hi> they ceaſe to be inwardly religious, and truly good men; but I drive it farther, That to <hi>Rebel</hi> is the ready way to ruine the Conſtitution of the outward, profeſt, and eſtabliſht <hi>Religion</hi> in a Nation. What need I look any farther for an example of this, when I have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58262:7"/>
a moſt remarkable proof in the Hiſtory of that King in my Text? King <hi>Solomon</hi> in his declining age <hi>fell,</hi> ſo as no <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> Prince can ever <hi>fall,</hi> unleſs he renounce his <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> from making <hi>Beauty</hi> his <hi>Idol,</hi> he <hi>fell</hi> even to worſhip the <hi>Pagan Deities,</hi> that is, Devils; for as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſays, <hi>The things which the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſacrifice, they ſacrifice to Devils, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> Yet <hi>all that while all Iſrael obey'd him,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed in the worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of God, as they might do without an inconſiſtence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Solomon</hi> was dead and gone, <hi>Jeroboam</hi> came in by <hi>Rebellion:</hi> for tho he was <hi>promis'd</hi> the Kingdom, 'tis ſaid the <hi>Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er was from the Lord,</hi> yet it was promis'd him only upon <hi>cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions,</hi> which he never performd, <hi>If thou wilt heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to all that I command thee as</hi> David <hi>my Servant did:</hi> But he would hearken to nothing that God commanded him, nor would he wait God's time as <hi>David</hi> had done. He drew <hi>Ten</hi> of the <hi>Tribes</hi> into <hi>Rebellion:</hi> But then the Prevailing <hi>Rebel</hi> for a Politic intereſt calls and compels (as much as in him lyes) all the Families in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every man of the ten Tribes, <hi>to Worſhip the Golden Calves:</hi> He forthwith <hi>Interdicts</hi> their going up to the Publick Worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Thus <hi>Idolatry</hi> was <hi>Eſtabliſht</hi> by a <hi>Law</hi> of a <hi>Rebels</hi> making, not only Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd but <hi>Eſtablisht</hi> by <hi>Jeroboam that made Iſrael to Sin,</hi> out of this one Rebellion came all that Sin: out of that one Sin of theirs came all their Calamity, and at lenght their Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: After this one <hi>Rebellion,</hi> their Church and State never had one good Day. It brought that <hi>Diſperſion</hi> upon thoſe Tribes, under which they are moſt Miſerable to this Day.</p>
            <p n="4">4 But now to diſpatch my <hi>Fourth</hi> and laſt Conſideration, 'Tis impoſſible to <hi>Honour and obey the King</hi> for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> without a fixt principle within us of <hi>that Fear of God</hi> which cannot fail to produce <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Obedience</hi> to all God'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Holy Commandments. Unleſs that Uniform <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to God be a <hi>National Vertue,</hi> How can a <hi>National bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> be expected from God? and without God's bleſſing how can we ook to proſper. 'Tis only the Dew of heaven can make a Kingdom flouriſh. If the <hi>Sweet Influences</hi> from above
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58262:7"/>
be reſtrain'd, the moſt hopeful Plant will by the next Eaſt-wind be blaſted in one night<hi>:</hi> all <hi>Second Cauſes</hi> are but viſible means in the Unſeen hand of the <hi>firſt,</hi> who if he be diſpleas'd, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes them move quite contrary even to their own Natural Tendency<hi>:</hi> God is not obliged to ſtand by the <hi>beſt Title,</hi> he may ſeize or diſpoſe of the Goodlieſt Inheritance as he Laſes Be a prince as powerful as <hi>Solomon;</hi> be a people as Obedient as <hi>Iſrael</hi> then was; God could raiſe up a little Fugitive Child <hi>Hadad</hi> that eſcap'd a Maſſacre in <hi>Edom,</hi> to be the Adverſary of K. <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Old Age, and <hi>Rezin</hi> a Fugitive <hi>Syrian</hi> to Reign in <hi>Damaſcus</hi> in defiance of <hi>him</hi> &amp; all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; to be the Father of thoſe <hi>Benhadads</hi> the ſcourges of <hi>Solomon's</hi> poſterity</p>
            <p>What Obligations then are upon us all of this <hi>happy Iſland</hi> as it has been dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of old) not to interrupt the bleſſings which this day ſeems to prepare for us, if we do our parts to make our ſelves fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to receive them? We have been the care of Heaven in all thoſe three great inſtances of my Text; The Title to the Crown being unqueſtionable; the King born for Empire, by nature and education fitted for Government, the people having now ſhewed <hi>themſelves</hi> obedient, and <hi>willing</hi> to be Govern'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>firſt,</hi> No <hi>Title</hi> by <hi>Gods immediate Deſignation</hi> (as it was in <hi>Solomon's</hi> Caſe) is now to be expected: No <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Viſion</hi> to be look't for: Nothing but ordinary <hi>Providence.</hi> But by this Providence we that are <hi>Subjects</hi> believe our Selves entitled to whatever we call Ours in this World. The beſt <hi>Title</hi> to any Inheritance of Ours is from our <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and the beſt of that kind is from Times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Memory. But who can pretend ſuch a <hi>Succeſſive Title</hi> to his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> as his Majeſty can ſhew to his <hi>Crown?</hi> How many Ages of our Anceſtors have wanted ſuch a Title as this? How are ſome other Nations like to be embroil'd with their Neighbours about their Succeſſion to the Crown, for want of this Bleſſing of a <hi>clear Title?</hi> A Bleſſing ſignally Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd to us by our late Sovereign Lord of <hi>bleſſed Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> For I muſt needs put you in mind, you that had the Honour to attend him on his Death-bed, How did we ſee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58262:8"/>
him like <hi>David bowing upon the Bed</hi> to his Succeſſor, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing his Royal Brother as his beloved <hi>undoubted Heir, Reſigning</hi> all to him (that was the kind word) to him that was more ready to Dye with Grief, than to take that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Reſignation.</p>
            <p>And as his Majeſties <hi>Title</hi> is moſt firm, ſo <hi>Secondly</hi> we have very promiſing hopes, from his gratious and glorious Beginings, of a <hi>Steddy Government.</hi> We have a King that has not been bred up at <hi>Eaſe</hi> in the Court of his Father, but in the School of Hardship and Affliction; (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tell us) <hi>worketh patience, and patience experince.</hi> Sure I may ſay without Imputation of Flattery, No Prince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Memory of man has come to a Crown with ſo vaſt a Stock of <hi>Experience.</hi> VVe have a King who underſtands and conſiders, that in an <hi>Hereditary Monarchy,</hi> 'tis the great peculiar advantage of the <hi>Prince</hi> as well as people, that their Intereſt is one and the ſame, their Happineſs ſo cloſely united, that (if I may apply the Apoſtle's expreſſion to this Caſe) <hi>Whether the body ſuffer, the Head ſuffers with it; or the Head be honoured, all the Members rejoyce with it.</hi> We have a King whom greatnes of Mind has ſeated as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Fear,</hi> as all the Hard-hearted impotent Paſſions which commonly Fear produces, are beneath him; and is himſelf ſo incapable of <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> that he would naturally Diſpiſe thoſe <hi>ſtrange Children</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> calls them) <hi>that ſhould Diſſemble with him:</hi> As <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Father of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, generouſly diſdain'd and diſgrac'd ſome Servants of his for being <hi>too good Courtiers,</hi> who (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates) upon a certain Tryal which the Emperor put upon them, on purpoſe to find who were honeſt, quitted their Chriſtian Profeſſion for fear of loſing their Places; but He retained and exalted thoſe who ſcorn'd to <hi>prevaricate</hi> with their <hi>God;</hi> for he Judged aright, That ſuch onely would be <hi>faithful</hi> to their King. Laſty, VVe have a <hi>King,</hi> who thô I will not ſay he was <hi>the Partner of the Empire</hi> while he was but a <hi>Subject</hi> (and yet I am not afraid of Envy if I own how much he <hi>Govern'd,</hi> ſince at the ſame time he knew ſo well
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58262:8"/>
how to <hi>obey,</hi> and ſet us all that perfect Example of Submſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) yet I may ſay he was <hi>particeps Curarum;</hi> the Sharer of his Royal Brothers Cares; That he felt the <hi>Thorns</hi> in his Crown; that he was all that while habitually practiſing <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> with <hi>Equity,</hi> governing according to <hi>Law,</hi> yet with tender <hi>Mercy,</hi> as the Royal <hi>Chief Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Charles the Merciful.</hi> And I preſume to Style him the very <hi>Similitude</hi> and <hi>Picture</hi> of <hi>Charles the Martyr.</hi> VVith ſuch <hi>Love as caſts out Fear</hi> we ſee in the Serene Aſpect of our <hi>Sovereign,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Line of his Bleſſed <hi>Fathers</hi> gratious <hi>Viſage,</hi> As <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperor triumpht in <hi>Eſſigie</hi> after his <hi>Death;</hi> ſo does that <hi>Glorified</hi> Prince in his <hi>Living</hi> Sacred <hi>Image</hi> on this Day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God has bleſt the King with an <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient People.</hi> After he might ſay with <hi>David</hi> in the moſt literal ſenſe, <hi>That the Waves and Storms had gone over him;</hi> after That alſo is overpaſt which <hi>David</hi> joyns with <hi>the rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sea, and the noiſe of its waves,</hi> that is, <hi>the madneſs of the People;</hi> In plain terms, after his Majeſties Deliverance, as well as Ours, from that abominable <hi>Excluding Bill;</hi> as great a Deliverance as that from the Sinking <hi>Gloceſter</hi> Frigot (for both which Preſervations we muſt always bleſs God) after all this; his Majeſties <hi>peacefull Entrance</hi> upon His Government, is a Sufficient, real, happy proof of <hi>an Obedient People.</hi> And as I muſt vehemently exhort you to perſerverance in that which is not only your <hi>Duty</hi> but your <hi>Practice;</hi> ſo I do in Effect commend your ſtrict adherence to your former <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> and to your <hi>Oaths of Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be thankfull to God then for thoſe Bleſſings you have, and to the King under whom they will be continued to you. Be ſatisfied with your condition; take heed of overturning or undermining the whole fabrick, becauſe you cannot have the room that you would chooſe in it, Take heed of de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>roving your Countrey to build your own houſe, take heed of ruining <hi>all,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you cannot mend your ſelves in this or that Particular. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Death is not all you are like to get by it: Take heed of that which follows: There's another Death to come after: God has warn'd you of it, <hi>They that Reſiſt ſhal receive to themſelves Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> As you would avoid this, take heed of that which leads to it. Do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58262:9"/>
that which is beſt for you here, and hereafter, beſt for the <hi>Publick</hi> and for your <hi>Private</hi> Intereſts; beſt for your ſelves and for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Children; as ever you deſire to leave them all theſe Blesſings.</p>
            <p>And for a powerful motive to his Sacred Majeſty to act well his Sovereign part for the good of this great people; the place it ſelf where he will be preſented anon with all the <hi>Regalia</hi> ſet in the ſeat of Empire, and made the Anointed of God; the place which is the Royal <hi>Golgotha,</hi> the burying place of Kings; where we have lately depoſited the venerable <hi>Remains</hi> of Majeſty; will put him in mind, from the <hi>Royal Prophet; Though Kings are made as Gods, they ſhall dye like men.</hi> And then I muſt put you all in mind, from the Apoſtle, <hi>That as it is appointed to men once to dye, ſo after death the Judgment.</hi> Mortality! Behold, conſider, and ſtand in awe; there's an acre of ground ſown with the richeſt ſeed that ever the earth received ſince the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s tranſgresſion occaſioned the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> like a <hi>corn of wheat to fall into the ground and dye.</hi> Think how much Royal duſt and aſhes is laid up in yonder Chappel; there the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> reſt quietly under one roof, there does Queen <hi>Mary</hi> &amp; her Siſter Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> lye cloſe together, their aſhes do not part. In the ſtory of <hi>Polinices</hi> and <hi>Eteocles,</hi> two Brothers rivals for a Crown; we are told their ſmoke divided into two <hi>Pyramids</hi> as it aſcended from one Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pile: But here theſe duſts do as kindly mingle, as all the old Piques and Averſions are ſoundly aſleep with them. And ſo ſhall we be ere long<hi>:</hi> moſt of us in a meaner lodging, but all of us in the <hi>duſt of death.</hi> A great King, upon ſight of a vaſt concourſe of his Subjects, wept at the very thought, that in a few years there would not be left alive ſo much as one of them. And well may we as ſeriouſly, though not ſo ſadly reflect, that when this numerous glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbly ſhall break up hence, we may e'ne adjourn our meeting to the general reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. But if we put into the Scale that laſt moſt weighty conſideration, that <hi>God shall bring every work into Judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good, or whether it be evil;</hi> Then from theſe Premiſſes that inference will be forcible indeed which <hi>Solomon</hi> makes at the end of his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, Let us hear</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the concluſion of the whole matter; Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man.</hi> This is all that God expects from the greateſt <hi>King,</hi> yet leſs God will not accept from the meaneſt Subject.</p>
            <p>Let but this <hi>one thing neceſſary</hi> be thoroughly done, then we may be able to uſe in our own behalf thoſe words of a King, <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea, bleſſed are the people who have the Lord for their God.</hi> Then may we hope from the Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſee with joyful eyes ſuch a miracle of happineſs in this World, as here we cannot read of but with admiration. that <hi>God will magnifie the King (as he did</hi> Solomon) <hi>exceedingly in the ſight of all</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and beſtow upon him ſuch Royal Majeſty as has not been on any King before him in</hi> Iſrael. And may both their Majeſties after the longeſt poſſeſſion of all earthly Greatneſs, with as lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le uneaſineſs as ever any Crowns brought along with them, at laſt ſee God, and Reign with Chriſt in heavenly Serene Glory for ever and ever: And <hi>let all the people ſay,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
